Guide to the John White Geary Mexican War Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John White Geary Mexican War papers
1846-1848
WA MSS S-585
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.8
(4 boxes) + 2 broadside folders, 1 rolled item
The collection consists of correspondence, military orders, muster rolls, and family material. Letters from John Geary's wife, Margaret, and brother, Edward, reflect political thinking on the national level. There is material from court martial proceedings, including the charges against Capt. Samuel H. Montgomery.
Geary, John White, 1819-1873
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Other Geary collections at the Beinecke are the John White Geary Papers (WA MSS 212), the John White Geary Business Papers (WA MSS S-209), and a letter from Geary to Major General Persifor Smith (WA MSS S-218).
Existence and Location of Copies
Available on microfilm.
JOHN WHITE GEARY
John White Geary was both soldier and politician; he served in the Mexican War and was later Territorial Governor of Kansas and Governor of Pennsylvania. At the outbreak of the Mexican War, Geary was Captain of the American Highlanders, which were attached to the "Cambria Legion." He and his company joined the 2nd Regiment of the Pennsylvania Volunteers at Pittsburgh, where he was elected Lieutenant Colonel. The regiment arrived at Vera Cruz April 11, 1847, via New Orleans and the Lobos Islands, and participated in Scott's advance to Mexico City. Colonel Roberts, the commander of the Regiment, was in such bad health that his responsibilities were left primarily to Geary. In the attack on Chapultepec Geary led the assault upon the fortress, and was placed in charge of this fortress upon its capture. Geary remained there on duty until the end of the war, being elected Colonel of his regiment on the death of Roberts.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, military orders, muster rolls, and family material. Letters from Geary's wife, Margaret, and brother, Edward, reflect political thinking on the national level. Captain Samuel H. Montgomery, a brother officer, sent letters back to Pennsylvania from Mexico in which he discredited the commander of the 2nd Regiment of Pennsylvania Volunteers, Colonel Roberts, and the officers under him, especially Geary. As these letters appeared in the Pennsylvania Argus, which was printed in Geary's home town of Greensburg, Pennsylvania, Geary's wife and brother were able to convey the public sentiment and reaction to the letters.
These papers also include a number of courts martial proceedings and sentences, including the charges preferred against Samuel H. Montgomery by Geary. There are also general military orders and reports which list the names of many of the men who deserted, were wounded, or killed in Geary's regiment.
An appended alphabetical listing of correspondents and dates of their letters is taken from the description of the Geary Mexican War Papers that appears as entry #93 in A Catalogue of the Frederick W. & Carrie S. Beinecke Collection of Western Americana compiled by Jeanne M. Goddard and Charles Kritzler (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1965). The correspondence is currently arranged chronologically; this appendix was included to enable readers to identify specific correspondents included in the collection.
Appendix: Alphabetical List of Correspondents
This listing is taken from the description of the Geary Mexican War Papers, entry #93 in A Catalogue of the Frederick W. & Carrie S. Beinecke Collection of Western Americana compiled by Jeanne M. Goddard and Charles Kritzler (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1965). The correspondence is currently arranged chronologically; this appendix was included to enable readers to identify specific correspondents within the collection.
Geary, John White. Copy of a letter to General George Gibson. July 20, 1847. Unsigned. 1 p.
---- Letter to Captain J. Hooker. January 31, 1848. 2 pp.
---- Charges and specifications preferred against Captain Samuel H. Montgomery, Assistant Quartermaster, U.S. Army. December 29, 1847. Signed by eight witnesses. 3 pp. With copy. 2 pp.
---- Copy of a letter to Major General Winfield Scott. October 31, 1847. Unsigned. 1 p.
---- Letter to His Excellency Francis Rawn Shunk. December 10, 1846. 1 p.
---- Copy of a letter to Daniel Sturgeon. 1847. Unsigned. 2 pp.
---- Letter to Major General Worth. October 29, 1847. 1 p.
---- Copy of a letter to Major General Worth. [n.d.] Unsigned. 2 pp.
---- Copy of a letter to George C. K. Zahm. [n.d.] Unsigned. 3 pp.
---- Report of the battle of Chapultepec to Lieutenant Lovell. September 15, 1847. 9 pp.
---- Copy of a letter for a plan for the consolidation of the 2d Regiment, Pennsylvania Volunteers. January 20, 1848. Unsigned. 1 p.
---- Anecdote of Santa Anna. [n.d.] Unsigned. 2 pp.
Armstrong, I. L. Letter to Geary. December 13, 1848. 1 p.
Armstrong, James. Letter to Geary. September 14, 1847. 1 p.
Bibb, Titus P. Atticus. Certification that Geary served on the military commission. May 13, 1848. 1 p.
Black, Samuel. Letter to Geary. March 15, 1847. 3 pp.
---- Letter to Colonel Childs, Military Governor of Jalapa. May 25, 1847. 1 p.
Black, Samuel W. Copy of a letter to His Excellency James K. Polk. February 5, 1848. 1p.
Bowman, George W. Letter to Geary. January 13, 1848. 1 p.
---- Letter to Geary. February 14, 1848. 2 pp.
---- Letter to Geary. April 12, 1848. 1 p.
Brindle, William. Letter to Geary. November 14, 1848. 1 p.
Browattan, E. & Co. Letter to Geary. January 25, 1848. 1 p.
Caskey, Robert. Letter to Geary. November 24, 1848. 1 p.
Conrad, James M. Letter to Geary. November 29, 1848. 1 p.
Cresswell, John. Letter to Geary. December 29, 1846. 1 p.
Daniels, Joseph. Letter to Geary. October 28, 1847. 1 p.
Davis, George T. M. Letter to Colonel Roberts. May 13, 1847. 1 p.
Donough, Andrew. Letter to Geary. January 1, 1848. 1 p.
Dutton, Benjamin F. Letter to Geary. August 8, 1848. 1 p.
Everhart, E. V. Letter to Geary. March 1847. 4 pp.
Fairfield, John W. Contract drawn up for chartering the ship General Veazie. January 12, 1847. Signed by Thomas B. Eastland. 4 pp.
Forster, W. Letter to Geary. September 2, 1848. 1 p.
Frick, Clarence H. Letter to Geary. December 13, 1847. 1 p.
---- Letter to Colonel Roberts. April 8, 1847. 1 p.
Geary, Edward R. Sixteen letters to his brother, John W. Geary. December 28, 1846-November 16, 1848. 50 pp.
Geary, Margaret A. Six letters to her husband, John W. Geary. April 8, 1847- May 22, 1848 [n.d.] 16 pp.
Gibson, George. Letter to Geary. December 4, 1847. 1 p.
Graves, R. L. Letter to Assistant Joseph Daniels. October 28, 1847. Signature only. 1 p.
Guthrie, John B. Letter to Geary. June 16, 1848. 2 pp.
Hacker Brother and Company. Two letters to Geary. August 4, October 11, 1848. 2 pp.
Hagner, Peter. Letter to Geary. March 6,1848. 1 p.
Hambright, Henry A. Letter to Geary concerning the battle of Chapultepec. September 14, 1847. 8 pp.
Hare, Nicholas. Letter to Geary. July 1, 1848. 1 p.
Heistand, I. D. Letter to Geary. January 11, 1847. 1p.
Henry, William. Letter to Geary. July 8, 1848. 2 pp.
Heyer, Charles H. Letter to Geary concerning the wounded at Chapultepec. September 15, 1847. 1 p.
Humphreys, John. Letter to Geary. October 2, 1848. 2 pp.
Irvine, Andrew. Letter to Geary. January 18, 1848. 2 pp.
Jackson, R. M. S. Letter to Geary. December 18, 1848. 1 p.
Jones, Roger Letter to Lieutenant John Keeffe. February 14, 1848. 2 pp.
Klotz, Robert. Letter to Geary. September 5, 1848. 1 p.
Litzinger, Charles. Letter to Geary. May 25, 1848. 2 pp.
Loeser, Thomas S. Form letter filled in to Geary. September 5, 1848. 1 p.
Logan, David. Letter to his brother-in law, J. W. Geary. March 20, 1848. 4 pp.
Logan, William W. Five letters to his brother-in-law, J. W. Geary. January 8- June 8 [n.d.] 14 pp.
McDermit, James. Letter to Geary. May 20, 1848. 1p.
McFarland, George R. Letter to Geary. May 14, 1848. 3 pp.
McGowan, George. Letter to Geary. May 21, 1848. 1 p.
Mackall, William W. Letter written to Geary for General Worth. November 2, 1847. 1 p.
---- Letter to Geary. November 15, 1847. 1 p.
McKamey, Alexander. Letter to Geary. November 8, 1847. 1 p.
McNamara, Robert. Letter to Geary. June 5, 1848. 1 p.
McWilliams, Peter H. Two letters to Geary. March 15, April 4, 1848. 4 pp.
Madson, Joseph L. Three letters to Geary. October 5, November 8, November 22, 1848. 3 pp.
Miller, F. W. Letter to Colonel Roberts. May 22, 1847. 1 p.
Montgomery, Samuel H. Letter to Geary. December 30, 1846. 1 p.
Moorhead, J. K. Letter to Geary. December 12, 1848. 1 p.
O'Neill, J. C. Letter to Geary. December 14, 1848. 1 p.
Patterson, Robert. Letter to Geary. March 15, 1848. 1 p.
Pearce, John C. Letter to Geary. December 29, 1846. 1 p.
Pennsylvania Infantry. 2d Regiment, 1847-1848. Testimonial that Captain Montgomery's statement, which was printed in the paper about the Regiment, was false. December 9, 1847. Signed by the officers of the Regiment. 3 pp.
Porter, Robert. Letter to Geary. February 27, 1848. 1 p.
Potts, James. Letter to Geary. May 30, 1848. 2 pp.
Reed, Robert H. Letter to Geary. November 14, 1848. 1 p.
Stifley, John. Letter to Geary. October 1848. 1 p.
Thomas, Lorenzo. Copy of a letter to Major O. Cross. May 17, 1848. 1 p.
Todd, Andrew. Letter to Geary. September 5, 1848. 2 pp.
Williams, Edward C. Letter to Geary about the battle of Chapultepec. September 14, 1847. 1 p.
Wilson, S. S. Letter to Geary. May 5, 1847. 1 p.
Chapultepec, Battle of, Mexico City, Mexico, 1847; Mexican War, 1846-1848 -- Campaigns; Soldiers -- Pennsylvania; United States -- Politics and government -- 1815-1861; Bowman, George W.; Geary, Edward R., 1811-1886; Geary, John White, 1819-1873; Geary, Margaret A., d. 1853; Logan, William W.; Madson, Joseph L.; Montgomery, Samuel H., d. 1864; Scott, Winfield, 1786-1866; Worth, William Jenkins, 1794-1849; United States. Army. Pennsylvania Infantry, 2d
- Correspondence, Series I; 0.2
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, consists of incoming
  and outgoing correspondence filed together. Many
  of the letters are fragile; care should be taken
  in handling them.
  - Correspondence, 1846 Dec (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1847 Jan-Mar (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1847 Apr-May (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1847 Jun-Jul (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1847 Sep (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1847 Oct-Dec (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1848 Jan (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1848 Feb (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1848 Mar (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1848 Apr (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1848 May (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1848 Jun-Aug (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1848 Sep-Oct (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1848 Nov-Dec (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Military Papers, 1846-1848; Series II; 0.4
  Series II, Military Papers, is arranged by
  document type. Many of these papers are fragile
  care should be taken in handling them.
  - Accounts, receipts, refunds, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Accounts, receipts, refunds, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Accounts, receipts, refunds, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Accounts, receipts, refunds (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Stored also in: Oversize, box 4,
    folder 64
  - Courts-Martial and Sentences Against, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 20-24)
  - Courts-Martial and Sentences Against, 1848 Apr (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Courts-Martial and Sentences Against (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Election papers, 1847-48 (Box 2, Folder 27-30)
    Lists of votes polled for Colonel,
    Lieutenant Colonel and Major of the
    Regiment
    Stored also in: Oversize box 4,
    folder 65
    Stored also in: Oversize broadside,
    folder 71
  - List of prisoners, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Orders, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 32-38)
  - Orders, 1848 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Orders, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Promotions and recommendations, 1847-48 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Promotions and recommendations (Box 2, Folder 42)
    folder 66
  - Reports, morning and monthly, 1847-48, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 43)
    folder 67
  - Other Reports: absences, desertions, discharges, killed, resigned, sick and wounded, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 44-45)
  - Other Reports: absences, desertions, discharges, killed, resigned, sick and wounded, 1848, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Supplies, 1847 Dec 27 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Regimental rolls, 1847-48, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 48-50)
    folders 68-70
    Stored also in: Oversize, broadside
    folder 72
    Stored also in: Oversize, art folder
    73
- Additional Papers, Date: 1848, 1856; Series III; 0.2
  Series III, Additional Papers, is arranged
  by format.
  - WRITINGS BY JOHN WHITE GEARY
    - Address delivered to the soldiers of his regiment before its discharge from the Mexican War, [1848] (Box 3, Folder 51)
      With typescript
    - Draft of a political speech in support of Lewis Cass, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Draft of a speech on behalf of the "Cambria Volunteers", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - ADDITIONAL PAPERS
    - Petition by Geary for advancement in Masonry, 1848 Jul 12 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Second Annual Circular of The Montezuma Society, [1856] (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Mr. Hervey Sparks' calling card, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS
    - Cartes-de-visite, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 57-60)
    - Cabinet card photographs (Box 3, Folder 61-63)
- Oversize, 2
  Oversize contains material from Series II,
  arranged in box order.
  - Accounts, receipts, refunds (from Series II), 1846-48, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Election papers (from Series II), 1847-48 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Promotions and recommendations (from Series II) (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Reports, morning and monthly (from Series II), 1847-48, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Regimental rolls (from Series II), 1847-48, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 68-70)
  - Election papers, 1847-48 (Box bsd, folder 71)
  - Regimental rolls, 1847-48, n.d. (Box bsd, folder 72)
  - Regimental rolls, 1847-48, n.d. (Box art, Folder 73)